Guide to the James E. Nathanson papers, 1981-1994
Special Collections Research Center, The Gelman Library, The George Washington University
James E. Nathanson papers, 1981-1994
Nathanson, James E.
MS2049
95 Linear feet
Collection contains reports, articles, and correspondence dating from 1981-1994. The files were created by Nathanson and his staff during his two consecutive terms as a member of the Council of the District of Columbia.
The George Washington University, The Gelman Library, Special Collections Research Center 2130 H. St. NW Washington, D.C. 20052 Phone: 202-994-7549 Email:
Information for Users
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
James E. Nathanson donated these records in 1995.
Historical or Biographical Note
James E. Nathanson was member of the Council of the District of Columbia from 1987-94. He served Ward Three.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains reports, articles, and correspondence. The material dates from 1981-94. The files were created by Nathanson and his staff during his two consecutive terms as a member of the Council of the District of Columbia.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: General office files, Committee files, and In-active files.
Subject Terms
Individuals
Nathanson, James E.
Corporate Entities
District of Columbia. City Council
Topics
District of Columbia. City Council; James E. Nathanson papers
Geographic Locations
Washington (D.C.)
Detailed Description of the Records
- General office files, 1987-1994, MS2049 Series 1; 28 Linear feet
  This series contains reports, correspondence, and research files. The years cover 1987-94. This material was created by James E. Nathanson and his staff during his time as a member of the Council of the District of Columbia. The subjects covered by this material include: housing, mental health, zoning, ABC regulations, Cleveland Park, traffic, real property tax, and sports.
  - Housing-Medicaid, 1990-1992, undated (Box 1)
  - Mental Health-Public Space Commission, 1990-1992, undated (Box 2)
  - Public Space-Solid Waste, 1990-1992, undated (Box 3)
  - Sports-Tort Reform, 1990-1992, undated (Box 4)
  - Tourism-Transportation, 1990-1992, undated (Box 5)
  - Trees-Zoning, 1990-1992, undated (Box 6)
  - Zoning-Reading Files A-Z, 1990-1993, undated (Box 7)
  - ABC Regulations-Children and Youth, 1993, undated (Box 8)
  - Cleveland Park Historical Society-Housing, 1993, undated (Box 9)
  - Housing Assistance-Public Space, 1993, undated (Box 10)
  - Real Property Taxes-Traffic Adjudication, 1993, undated (Box 11)
  - Traffic Adjudication-Reading Files A-Z, 1993-1994, undated (Box 12)
  - Abandoned Cars-Community Based Residential Facilities (CBRF), 1994, undated (Box 13)
  - CBRF-Economic Development, 1994, undated (Box 14)
  - Education-Nathanson Clippings, 1994, undated (Box 15)
  - Nathanson Files-University of the District of Columbia (UDC), 1994, undated (Box 16)
  - Traffic Adjudication-Zoning, 1994, undated (Box 17)
  - Appointment Books, 1987-1994; Constituent Request Forms, 1992, undated (Box 18)
  - Constituent Request Books, 1993-1994, undated (Box 19)
- Committee files, 1990-1994, MS2049 Series 2; 9 Linear feet
  This series contains correspondence and committee records for the Committee on the Judiciary. The material dates from 1990-94. These materials were created by James E. Nathanson and his staff during his time as a Council member of the Council of the District of Columbia.
  - Committee's on the Judiciary, Public Works, Finance and Revenue, and Georgetown Operation Facility, 1990-1994, undated (Box 20)
  - Committee on the Judiciary: Council for Court Excellence and Panhandling Subject File, 1992-1994, undated (Box 21)
  - Committee on the Judiciary: Corrections Subject Files and Oversight Hearing, 1993-1994, undated (Box 22)
  - Committee on the Judiciary: Corrections Correspondence Files and General Legislative Files, 1990-1994, undated (Box 23)
  - Committee on the Judiciary: Corrections Subject Files and Potomac Rehab Services, Inc., 1991-1993, undated (Box 24)
  - Committee on the Judiciary: Corrections and Criminal Justice Reform Subject Files, 1993-1994, undated (Box 25)
- In-active files, 1981-1989, MS2049 Series 3; 58 Linear feet
  This series contains correspondence, financial records, and research files that cover the years 1981-89. These files were created by James E. Nathanson and his staff during his time as a council member of the Council of the District of Columbia. Subjects in this series include: human rights, health care, housing, taxes, transporation, civic associations, traffic, statehood, and development.
  - Postal Service-Public Activities Thank You's, 1987 Files, undated (Box 26)
  - Invitations Accepted and Appointments, June-July 1988; Development, Connecticut Ave. and Historic Preservation, 1987 Files, undated (Box 27)
  - Recycling-Thank You's, 1988 Files, undated (Box 28)
  - Invitations Accepted and Appointments, Sept.-Dec. 1988, undated (Box 29)
  - Development Zoning, Home Occupations-Education, 1987 Files, undated (Box 30)
  - Reading Files A-Z, 1988; Abandoned Vehicles-Business, 1988 Files, undated (Box 31)
  - Human Rights, New York Law-Memorials, 1987 Files, undated (Box 32)
  - Utilities, 1987 Files; National Airport, 1981-1983, undated (Box 33)
  - Health Care Decisions-Mental Health, 1987 Files, undated (Box 34)
  - Health Nursing-Housing, 1987 Files, undated (Box 35)
  - Budget Hearings for Special Committees, 1988-1989, undated (Box 36)
  - Housing, Berkshire-Housing, Rental, 1987 Files, undated (Box 37)
  - Reading File A-Z, 1987, undated (Box 38)
  - Housing, Rent Control-Human Rights, JEN Amendment to Human Rights Law, 1987 Files, undated (Box 39)
  - Citizens-Civic Associations, 1987 Files, undated (Box 40)
  - FY 89 Budget and FY 88 Supplemental Budget for Committees, 1988-1989, undated (Box 41)
  - Invitations Accepted and Appointments, Jan.-May 1987, undated (Box 42)
  - Taxes-Transportation, Air, 1987 Files, undated (Box 43)
  - City Services, Streets and Sidewalks-Consumer Affairs, No-Fault Insurance, 1987 Files, undated (Box 44)
  - ANC's-Committee of the Whole (COW), 1988 Files, undated (Box 45)
  - FY 89 Budget and FY 88 Supplemental Budget for Committees, 1988-1989, undated (Box 46)
  - Traffic Adjudication-Utilities, Electric; Administrative Council Auditor, 1987 Files, undated (Box 47)
  - Unemployment-Workmen's Compensation; Council Auditor-Mayor's Office, 1987 Files, undated (Box 48)
  - Crime, Firearms-Development, Building Permits, 1987 Files, undated (Box 49)
  - Development, Wisconsin Ave.-Development, Zoning, 1987 Files, undated (Box 50)
  - FY 88 Supplemental Budget for Special Committees and FY 89 Budget Hearings, 1988-1989, undated (Box 51)
  - Recreation-Statehood, 1987 Files, undated (Box 52)
  - Telephone Message Pads and File on Constituent Funds, 1987, undated (Box 53)
  - 1983 Comprehensive Plan, 1983-1986, undated (Box 54)
  - Statehood-Taxes, 1987 Files, undated (Box 55)
  - 1983 Comprehensive Plan, 1983-1986, undated (Box 56)
  - Administrative Auditor-Mayor's Office, 1988 Files, undated (Box 57)
  - Animals-City Services, Stop Signs and Lights, 1987 Files, undated (Box 58)
  - Labeled, Empty File Folders, undated (Box 59)
  - Invitations Accepted and Appointments, Jan.-May 1988, undated (Box 60)
  - Condolences-Gas Company, 1988 Files, undated (Box 61)
  - Boards and Commissions, Citizens-Civic Associations, 1988 Files, undated (Box 62)
  - Gay Community-Requests, 1988 Files, undated (Box 63)
  - Invitations Accepted and Appointments, Jan.-July 1989, undated (Box 64)
  - Invitations Accepted and Appointments, June-Dec. 1987, undated (Box 65)